Guide to the Jane Lathrop Stanford Papers SC0033B
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Personal and miscellaneous papers, 1872-1952; Series 3; 0.5 Linear Feet
  - Passports, 1883-1902 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - TLS [Miki] Saito introducing J. L. Stanford, 28-Apr-02
    - passport of L.Stanford and J.L.Stanford signed by Thomas F. Bayard, May 24, 1888
  - Poetry, commemorative, 1884-1902 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Frank Allyn, "There Is No Death," (bd. typescript), Sep 21, 1887
    - C. L. Frye, "1876-1886" (mss), Jan 23, 1891
    - Dr. Guthrie, "The Watcher at the Gate," (mss), undated
    - San Francisco Girls' High School, senior class, "Poem in Memory of Leland Stanford," (ptd), 1884
    - Mrs. Kate Scott, "Stanford University," (mss), 1893
    - Robert Whitaker, God Garners No Green Grain, (ptd), 1902
    - 4 anonymous mss poems
  - Poetry, commemorative: "In the Summer Land" by Jennie Hicks, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Bound volume of mss poems with illuminated capitals and some full page paintings.
  - Religious publications printed for or prepared by J. L. Stanford (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Statue - Junipero Serra (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Photostats of request and permission to erect on site of old fort at Monterey, clips, photo of statue.
  - Travel ephemera, 1883-1903 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Tributes (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - "A Sonnet" by Alphonso G. Newcomer, poem
    - "Charity" by A.F. Scott, poem
- Death and estate papers, 1894-1921; Series 4; 0.5 Linear Feet
  This series includes copies of her will and other estate papers; correspondence of David Starr Jordan and medical reports regarding her death; copy of the coroner's inquest on her death; memorials; and letters of condolence.
  - Estate - Living Trust, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    1903 lease of San Francisco and Palo Alto residences to Jane Stanford, signed by S.F. Leib, Geo. E. Crothers (2 cc).
  - Estate - Northern Railway of California Bonds, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Documents re bonds sold by Board of Trustees to estate of J. L. Stanford; documents signed by Chas. G. Lathrop, T.S. Crothers, and Timothy Hopkins.
  - Estate - conveyance of personal property to Board of Trustees, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Covers residences in San Francisco, Palo Alto, and Washington, DC, and their contents.
  - Wilson and Wilson, attorneys, 1894-1900 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Documents to and from lawyers re: services and will receipts from Wilson and Wilson, appointment of Russell J. Wilson as attorney to J. L. Stanford, accounts, memorandum in J. L. Stanford's hand re wills held by Wilson and Wilson
  - Will, holograph copy of 1899 will (in Jane Stanford's handwriting) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Will, holograph copy of 1899 will (photocopy) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Will, changes to be made (in Jane Stanford's handwriting), 1900 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Will, 3 copies, with covers, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1903 will as printed in The Daily Palo Alto (photocopy), 1905 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, S. F. Leib to Jeannie L. Lawton re provisions of J. L. Stanford's will, 1905-03-06 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters and papers re: death of Jane Lathrop Stanford, 1905-1921 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - TL to David Starr Jordan and manuscript and typescript copies of the testimony of Ernest C. Waterhouse, 1905 Mar 14
    - M.D. statement of conclusion re J. L. Stanford's death signed by David Starr Jordan and Timothy Hopkins, 1905 Mar 16
    - AL David Starr Jordan to Samuel F. Leib, 1905 Mar 22
    - TL [David Starr Jordan] to Mountford S. Wilson, 1905 Mar 22
    - TL [David Starr Jordan] to Samuel F. Leib listing 12 points re: the death, 1905 Mar 22
    - TL [David Starr Jordan] to Montford S. Wilson re bicarbonate of soda, 1905 Mar 23
    - TL [David Starr Jordan] to Carl S. Smith re: the physicians, 1905 Mar 24
    - ALS Jared G. Smith to David Starr Jordan re: reliability of Dr. Story, 1907 Jan 28
    - TL [David Starr Jordan] to Ray Lyman Wilbur re: Jane Stanford's death, 1921 May 18
  - Coroner's inquest in re: Death of Jane L. Stanford (photocopy), 1905 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Funeral and Memorial Services, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Printed notice: General arrangements for the funeral of Mrs. Jane Lathrop Stanford, Friday March the 24, 1905
    - Order of Exercises, Memorial Church, 24-Feb-05
    - Order of Service, Mausoleum, 24-Feb-05
    - Memorial Service, 28-Feb-05
    - Typescript and manuscript drafts for memorial services, 1905
    - Photo of wreaths at Mausoleum, 1905
  - Memorials, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 14-16)
    Letters by George M. Bower, Jas. B. Hamilton, Chas.K. Field, Ellwood P. Cubberley, Jos. Swain, Aylett R. Cotton Jr., F.H. Wheelen, K. Ugeno (Japanese consul), Chas. W. Fay, C.W. Wright, Luther Burbank (Tel.), John T. Doyle, James Agler, M.H. Hyland, John P. Irish, Ben. Ide Wheeler (Tel.) ,Grace H. Gilmor, Ray Lyman Wilbur, J.C. Branner, and Jno. J. Sabin; lists of pall bearers and marshals; and poems.
  - Letters of condolence on death of Jane Stanford, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Letters of condolence on death of Jane Stanford, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- University matters, 1887-1904; Series 5; 1 Linear Feet
  Included in this series are agreements, correspondence, and legal papers pertaining to the administration of the University and to the Board of Trustees; her addresses to the Board of Trustees; amendments to the founding grant; and correspondence and other papers pertaining to the Library, the Church, and the Museum.
  - Agreements with Jordan, David Starr, 1894-1901 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - re: monthly sum for faculty salaries, 1894 Mar 6
    - re: support of the university, 1897 May 15
    - re: monthly sum for faculty salaries, 1899 Mar
    - re: monthly sum for faculty salaries, 1901 May 1
  - Amendments to Founding Grant, drafts of (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
    Manuscripts and typescripts, some duplicates, some contain explanatory statements not found in printed versions
  - Board of Trustees
    - Addresses to, 1897-1904 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - typescript copies of 1904 address, with copy of deed of Grant
      - typescript copies of 1897 May 29 address
      - typescript copy of 1899 May 31 address
    - Addresses to, 1897-1903 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      5 ptd. copies, several duplicates, 1897-1903; and 5 ptd. copies in 1 bound volume
    - Letters, 1896-1903 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - tel. from J. H. Choate, 189-
      - tel. from I.E. Gates, Sep 26, 1896
      - tels. from Thomas Hubbard and Stephen J. Field, Sep 29, 1896
      - copy of resignation of Irving M. Scott, May 11, 1898
      - ANS H. C. Nash to Charles Lathrop forwarding copy of Scott's resignation, Jan 30, 1899
      - TLS from Russell J. Wilson re papers sent by Mr. Leib, June 5, 1899
      - LS J. L. Stanford to S. F. Leib, deliver deeds to Bd. of Trustees, June 6, 1899
      - ALS S.F. Leib to J. L. Stanford, received documents (original and copy), 26-Jan-00
      - TL Henry R. Worthington to J. L. Stanford specifications of water pump being shipped, 8-Nov-00
      - J. L. Stanford to S. F. Leib re problem of more burials in Arboretum (specifically Rev. Dr. Brown), July 9, 1902
      - J. L. Stanford to Bd. of Trustees reasons for closing burial grounds in Arboretum [final version and drafts], July 9, 1902
      - TLS J. L. Stanford to S. F. Leib re her resignation from Board, May 29, 1903
      - TL Whitelaw Reid to Mr. Nicholson re Rev. Heber R. Newton and his resignation, June 13, 1903
      - TLS Crothers to J. L. Stanford, notice of meeting Dec. 26, 14-Dec-03
      - TLS Crothers to J. L. Stanford, notice of adjourned meeting Dec. 26, 14-Dec-03
    - List of bonds transferred by J. L. Stanford to Trustees, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Papers, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Conveyance of bonds and stocks, J. L. Stanford to Trustees, 1897-06-01
      - Instruction as to location of buildings and places to be kept free, 1897-06-01
    - Papers, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Deed. transfer of money for Leland Stanford Jr. chair of archeology and Egyptology, jewels, real and personal property, May 31, 1899
      - Power of Attorney to Trustees (3 cc), May 31, 1899
    - Papers, 1900-1903 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Notice of University property she is currently holding that should not be considered part of her personal estate (5 cc), 25-Jan-00
      - Organization of Trustees (2 cc), 1-Nov-01
      - Resignation of rights, July 6, 1903
      - Acceptance of election to Board of Trustees, July 6, 1903
    - Trust for the erection of Library, Assembly Hall [and others], 1897 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Statements to on various issues, Drafts (mostly holograph) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Book List: J. L. Stanford's books transferred from museum to library (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Budget, 1903-1904 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Mss. copies of correspondence between J. L. Stanford and David Starr Jordan. From the Horace Davis Papers
  - Constitutional Amendment, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Leib, Samuel F. to Lathrop, Charles G. re: $5000 for expenses, 1900 Oct 6
    - Lathrop, Charles G. to Leib, Samuel F. sends $5000, 1900-10-08
    - Leib, Samuel F. to Lathrop, Charles G. acknowledges receipt of $5000, 1900-10-09
    - Leib, Samuel F. to Lathrop, Charles G. balance due on expenses, 1900-12-22
    - receipt for balance due, 1900 Dec 26
  - Deed of Grant (3 photostatic copies) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Library (destroyed in 1906 earthquake), 1903-1905 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Letters among Clinton Day (architect), Jane Stanford, George Crothers, Charles Lathrop, and Charles Hodges; estimates and receipts; agreements with Clinton Day; power of attorney to three trustees for matters relating to library construction
  - Memorial Church, miscellany, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Inscriptions for Jane and Leland's parents and their placement in the church, signed by J. L. Stanford, with letter from John McGilvray regarding the note, 1935
  - Miscellany, 1887-1899 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Hopkins, Timothy to H. L. Dodge re payment for trustee dinner in honor of Stanfords, 1887-10-13
    - invitation to Hopkins, Timothy from Stanfords to come to Palo Alto for meeting with trustees, 1887-11-10
    - L. M. Rice to D. S. Jordan re Mrs. Stanford's purchase of library of Justice Field, 1899-05
    - Two poems and a story by Amelia W. Truesdell from the Sequoia presented to Mrs. Stanford, 1905
  - Museum building: Contract and specifications for Museum wings, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - New York Alumni Reunion, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Printed menu, invitation list, and telegrams and notes of acceptance, including those of A. Henry Suzzallo and Timothy Hopkins.
  - Opening Day speech, 1891-10-01 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Roble Hall Matron: application of Mrs. H.E. Wright, acceptance and statement of rules, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Ross Affair: Notebook containing David Starr Jordan's statement with exhibits and ptd. report of Committee of Economists (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Scholarship, Leland Stanford Jr., legal documents (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Sigma Nu Fraternity, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Fraternity to C. E. Hodges re bill for meals while house was being moved, 1898-10-27
    - Lathrop, Charles G. to C. E. Hodges re: Sigma Nu bill, 1898 Oct 29
  - Social events sponsored by J. L. Stanford or in honor of J. L. Stanford by students or trustees (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Thomas Welton Stanford Library: contents of cornerstone box, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - University leases: Sigma Alpha Epsilon House, "Bachelors Hall", and blank form (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Notice of completion of work...[photocopies], 1898-1899 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Legal documents [photocopies], 1900-1904 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Sculpture work on Memorial Church frieze, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - President's Office: costs/payments for construction of Library, Assembly Hall, etc., 1900 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Biographical materials, 1905-1975; Series 6; 0.5 Linear Feet
  Included are articles; radio and TV scripts; reminiscences by Mrs. O. P. Jenkins and Jessie K. Jordan; and drafts of Gunther Nagel's biography on Jane L. Stanford.
  - Berner, Bertha, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - ALS to Payson J. Treat with reminiscences and clippings, 1914
  - Crothers, George E. "The Educational Ideals of Jane Lathrop Stanford" (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Estler, Suzanne. "Jane Stanford and 19th Century Feminism", 1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Hopkins, Timothy, 1910 and undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Notes for a possible talk on J. L. Stanford, undated
    - Letter to Rev. Charles Gardner re J. L. Stanford, 1910-02-26
  - Jenkins, Mrs. O.P., Reminiscences (typescript), circa 1925 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Jordan, David Starr (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "Story of a Good Woman", 1909
    - "Jane Lathrop Stanford; A Eulogy", 1912
  - Jordan, Jessie K. reminiscences of the Stanfords, 1922-1927 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Memoirs of events following Leland Stanford's death, undated
    - Recollections of the Stanfords, read before the Palo Alto chapter of the DAR, (3 cc), 1927
    - Jane Lathrop Stanford 1828-1905, 1922
  - Miscellaneous, 1905-1923 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - letter to D.S. Jordan from F. A. Robbins re seeing J.L.Stanford's funeral procession at Honolulu, 1905 May 9
    - Lawrence, Mary V. T, Tribute to Mrs. Jane Lathrop Stanford and Mrs. Ellen Mason Colton read before the Sequoia Chapter, DAR, circa 1905
    - "The Church Chimes," Memorial Church, S. U., with essay on J.L.Stanford, [1923]
    - Peterson, Harry C., "Mrs. Leland Stanford's Wonderful Laces," Ladies' Home Journal, July 1905
  - Nagel, Gunther W., Your Friend, Jane Stanford, typescript draft copy (Box 1, Folder 9-13)
  - Radio and T.V. Scripts: "This is Your Home" [program on J. L. Stanford], 1945 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Unidentified notes on J.L. Stanford (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Clippings, 1892-1962; Series 7; 1.5 Linear Feet
  - Estate matters and biographical article by Ethel Ingalls, 1892-1894 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mostly re managing university finances, including article by Annie Laurie, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Inheritance tax case, endowment, estate distribution, 1896-1898 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Inheritance tax case, endowment, estate distribution, limiting women students, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bequest $30,000,000 endowment, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - N.Y. reunion, library, sued by Robert Schmid, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Reception for women students, retirement, Heber Newton resignation, Pres. Bd. of Trustees, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Poison mystery, death, funeral, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Misc. (includes undated newspaper in Japanese), 1940-1962 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Government suit, disposition of San Francisco residence, 1894-1897 (Box 2 OS, Folder 1)
  - Court decision, 1896 (Box 2 OS, Folder 2)
  - University affairs, 1902-1904 (Box 2 OS, Folder 3)
  - The Bulletin re: her death, 1905 (Box 2 OS, Folder 4)
  - Daily Palo Alto, re her death
    - 1905 Mar 1-1905 Mar 3 (Box 2 OS, Folder 5)
    - 1905 Mar 6-1905 Mar 7 (Box 2 OS, Folder 6)
    - 1905 Mar 8-1905 Mar 10 (Box 2 OS, Folder 7)
    - 1905 Mar 13-1905 Mar 14 (Box 2 OS, Folder 8)
    - 1905 Mar 16-1905 Mar 17 (Box 2 OS, Folder 9)
    - 1905 Mar 20-1905 Mar 22 (Box 2 OS, Folder 10)
    - 1905 Mar 23-24 (Box 2 OS, Folder 11)
    - 1905 Mar 27-1906 Feb (Box 2 OS, Folder 12)
  - re her death in other newspapers, 1905 Feb-Mar 2 (Box 2 OS, Folder 13)
  - re her death in other newspapers, 1905 Mar 3-6 (Box 2 OS, Folder 14)
  - re her death in other newspapers, 1905 Mar 8-1905 Mar 11 (Box 2 OS, Folder 15)
  - Obituary, California Christian Advocate, 1905 Mar 9 (Box 2 OS, Folder 16)
  - re her death in other newspapers, 1905 Mar 15-Dec 31 (Box 2 OS, Folder 17)
  - re her death and funeral, Palo Alto Times, 1905 Mar 24-Mar 30 (Box 2 OS, Folder 18)
  - Biographical, 1900-1949 (Box 2 OS, Folder 19)
- Resolutions and Memorials, Series 8
  - Stanford Alumni of Hawaii; resolution re Jane Stanford's death (calligraphy), 1905 Mar 7; ARCH_AM_00_278; 39 x 26 cm (Box 1)
  - Resolution re death of Jane Stanford, signed by members of Stanford Club of S.F., ARCH_AM_00_306; 45 x 39 cm (Box 1)